Hello Namaskar Jai Hind Vande Mataram.  You are watching
Jio News and we have brought for you
quick big news of selected importance from the country, world and your state and city.  But
before that, if you have not subscribed to our channel, then
subscribe to the channel and turn on the bell notification
and like and
share this video as much as possible.  Today's question for you before looking at the big news.
Which is the brightest and hottest planet in the solar system?  Option A
Mercury, Option B Mars, Option C Venus and
Option D Jupiter.  Answer this question by
commenting and tell us which state and city's
news do you want to see more?
Tell us by commenting so that we
can show more news of your state or city.  Let us now see
today's quick big news.
500 daughters in UP will get free scooties.
This is a first time voter, petrol
model or EV, it is not decided yet.  Yogi government is going to
play a big bet just before the UP assembly elections and this year it is preparing to give
free scooties to more than 500 meritorious daughters in UP.  The
government is going to fulfill
its promise made during the 2022 assembly elections
and a
budget of ₹400 crore has also been finalized for this.  The
government can get three big benefits by giving scooties in the election year.
First, the total number of voters in UP is
13.40 crore and among them 6.09 crore are
women.  By giving scooties, the government
wants to give a big message to the women voters.  Secondly,
most of the girls who will get free scooties will
vote for the first time in 2027 and
through the daughters, the government is giving the message of good thinking and good work
and thirdly, the opposition
makes an issue during the elections that the BJP did
not fulfill the promises it had made, hence the government is
moving rapidly in this direction.
Supreme Court said SIR is not illegal.   The
Election Commission can verify citizenship with conditions.
7.41 crore names deleted in SIR in 13 states and UTs.  The Supreme Court has declared the
Special Incentive Revision (SIR) of the voter list as
valid and constitutional.  The
bench of Chief Justice Surya Kant
said that the SIR is not arbitrary.  The Election Commission has the
right to conduct this process.   The
court said that the Election Commission can verify
citizenship to add or remove names from the voter list.
But this decision will be
limited only for electoral purposes and the Commission will not have the right to
finally declare any person as a non-citizen.   The
Supreme Court has directed the Election Commission to
send the names of those whose names have been removed from the voter list on the basis of doubtful citizenship to the Central Government within four weeks.  The SIR process, which started in Bihar in June 2025, has
so far been completed
in 10 states and three union territories.
During this period, names of 7 crore 41 lakh
voters have been removed and out of these, the
highest number of 2.89 crore names have been removed from Uttar Pradesh.
UCC bill passed in Assam, polygamy banned.
Now a law is applicable in the state for marriage, divorce and live-in.  The
Assam Assembly has
passed the Uniform Civil Code i.e. UCC Bill.
Under this, a uniform law will be applicable for all religions in matters like marriage, divorce,
inheritance and live-in relationship
and after the passage of this bill,
Assam has become the
third state to pass the UCC law after Uttarakhand and Gujarat.
CBI makes two more arrests in NEET case.
Among these, three students including a doctor and his son were made to appear for the exam.
So far 13 people have been
arrested.
CBI has arrested two more accused in the NEET paper leak case.  The
first accused has been identified
as Dr. Manoj Sirure and he is a
resident of Latur.  Dr. Manoj had
got the Chemistry question paper from accused PV Kulkarni for three students including the son of the coaching centre owner who is also an accused.  And the second accused caught there
is Tejas Harshad Kumar Shah.  He teaches Physics at
Dr. Abhang Prabhu Medical Academy APMA, a coaching centre based in Pune.
He had received the leaked Physics questions for the NEET exam
from the arrested accused Manisha Havaldar.
Investigation is underway to find out the entire link and conspiracy in this case.  The
CBI has so far conducted
searches at 49 locations in different locations and seized several important
documents, laptops and mobile phones.  A
total of 13 people have been arrested in this case so far.
Hyundai cars will become costlier by up to ₹12,800.   The
new prices will be implemented from June 1, 2026.   The
company took the decision due to rising input costs.
Hyundai Motor India cars are going to become
expensive from June 1, 2026.  The company has
decided to increase the prices of its cars by up to ₹12,800 and the new
prices will be decided depending on different models and variants.
Earlier, the company had issued a letter on
April 8, 2026 regarding the increase in prices.
But now,
considering the current market situation, it has been decided
to implement it from June 1.  The
company has taken this step with the aim of creating a balanced coordination between the current market
conditions and the interests of the customers.
BJUS founder Ravi Chandran sentenced to 6 months in
jail.  Singapore court
found him guilty of concealing property and papers.  A fine of ₹67 lakh was
also imposed.  BJU Ravindran, owner of India's first major
education tech company BJUs, has been
sentenced to six months in prison by a Singapore court.  The court found
that Ravi Chandran had
concealed important documents related to his property and
disobeyed court orders, which was
considered contempt of court.  According to the Singapore court,
Ravindranath had been continuously ignoring orders to provide
information related to his properties since April 2004.
Now when
he repeatedly did not
obey the court, the court declared him guilty
and ordered him to be sent to jail.   The
court has asked Ravindranath to surrender before the authorities immediately.
Air India will reduce around 800 domestic
flights a week.  IndiGo
will also reduce flights by 7%.  Impact of expensive fuel and increased operation costs.
Tata Group's airline Air India is
cutting around 800 domestic flights every week.  This change will be effective from June to August
2026 and the company has taken this decision
due to rising jet fuel prices.  At the
same time, a news report
claimed that Indigo can also reduce its domestic flights by
5 to 7%.  Air
India currently operates around 4,400
flights every week, including around
3,600 domestic and 800 international flights.  The
company has announced a reduction in domestic flights by 22%.
Air India
said it will closely monitor market demand and operating
conditions and will
consider resuming flight operations as soon as conditions become normal and stable.
Iran says draft of agreement with America is
ready.  Ship movement will start in Hormoz within 1 month.
America
will lift the naval blockade.  Iran has claimed that the
initial draft of a possible agreement with America has been
prepared.
According to Reuters, Iran's state TV has claimed to have
received an initial and unofficial document.
In which the framework of the US-Iran agreement has been
prepared.
According to the draft, America will remove its military presence from around Iran
and end the naval blockade.  In
return, Iran will restore the movement
of commercial ships in the Strait of Hormuz
to pre-war levels within 30 days.  The
report said that this
arrangement will not apply to US military ships
and the movement of ships in Muz will be
jointly managed by Iran and Oman.   The
names of nine Islamic places in Pakistan will
not be changed.  The Hindu Sikh era was to be named.  The
decision was taken after protests from fundamentalists.
Maryam Nawaz's government in Pakistan's Punjab province has temporarily postponed the decision to restore the
old names of Lahore's streets, squares and areas.   The
names the government wanted to restore
included many from the Hindu and Sikh eras.  The
government took this step
after growing protests from radical groups and on social media.
Some people gave it a religious colour,
calling it an attempt to bring back Hindu and Sikh identity.
Lahore Deputy
Commissioner Captain (Retd) Mohammad Ali Ejaz
told Pakistani newspaper Dawn that no
final decision has been taken yet.   The
hostel where the Ahmedabad plane crash took place will be rebuilt.
₹15 crore will be spent on the super specialty hostel.  There
will be 236 doctors.  A new modern super specialty hostel will be built in place of the hostel on which a plane crashed in Ahmedabad, Gujarat
in June last year.  The
Gujarat government has decided to build a nine-storey hostel and canteen block
at the New Mental Campus at Asarwa near the Civil Hospital at a cost of ₹15
crore.
Minister of State for Health Praful Pansaria
said that Tata Airlines will give Rs 53.12 crore to the Health Department as compensation for the
four block canteen and substation building of Atulya One damaged in the plane crash.
There will be accommodation for 236 doctors.
Tisha case accused Samarth
on CBI remand till 29th, hearing in High Court on anticipatory bail of retired judge.
Accused of not cooperating in the investigation.
In the case of death of actress Pisha Sharma, the SIT
presented the accused husband Samarth Singh in Bhopal court on Wednesday.  The court
sent him on CBI remand till May 29.  Meanwhile, the
petition seeking cancellation of anticipatory bail of retired judge and mother-in-law Giribala Singh is being
heard in the court of Justice Dev Narayan Mishra of the MP High Court
and the MP government and Tisha's father Navnidhi
Sharma had filed objections to the anticipatory bail.
Senior
advocate Siddharth Luthra appeared for Tisha's father.
High Court's decision: Asaram will have to
surrender.  The sentence remains intact.
Two accused acquitted in case of sexual harassment of a minor.
The decision was announced after about 1 month.  Rajasthan
High Court Jodhpur pronounced its verdict on Asaram's sentence on the morning of 27 May.  The
High Court has upheld the
life imprisonment sentence in the case of sexual assault on a minor.
This decision was given by the division bench of Justice Arun Monga and Justice Yogendra Kumar Purohit.
Co-accused Shilpi and Sharad Chand have been acquitted in the case.
Asaram is currently on interim bail.
But now he will have to surrender.
World's second largest
battery energy storage system launched in Gujarat.  It has the
capacity to provide 24-hour electricity to entire Goa and cities like Indore.  India has created history
in green energy transition.
Adani Green
Energy Limited, the renewable energy company of Adani Group, has commissioned Battery Energy Storage System (BESS) with a
total capacity of 3.37 GWh at Khavda on the Kutch border.
This is the
largest battery storage project built at a single location in the entire world except China.  The electricity generated
from solar or wind energy will be stored in the batteries kept here and will be
supplied to any city as and when required.  Let us tell you
that with this system, built in a record 10 months,
entire cities like Goa, Indore, Chandigarh or in
other words, 10 lakh houses can be provided electricity 24 hours a day.
This storage can keep 1.2 crore
LED bulbs burning continuously for 10 hours.
FIR registered against Mamata Banerjee in Siliguri.  An FIR has been registered against
former West Bengal Chief Minister
Mamata Banerjee at the Siliguri Cyber ​​Police
Station for calling Sanatan a dirty religion at an Eid event in Kolkata in 2025.  Mamata
Banerjee is accused of making objectionable remarks about Sanatan and Hindu religion
during the Eid program held in Kolkata in 2025.  The
controversy is regarding the statement in
which he was accused of using words like dirty religion.
However, no response has come
from Mamata Banerjee on this matter so far.
This complaint has been
filed by lawyer Rinki Chatterjee Singh.
He says that the statement has hurt the religious sentiments of the people
and Rinki has
demanded action from the police in the matter.
Claim: Karnataka CM Siddharth Ramaiah
may resign.  Ministers were
invited for breakfast.  Preparations to make DK Shiv Kumar the
Chief Minister.  Karnataka
Chief Minister Siddharth Ramaiah
may resign on Thursday.  The party can make
Deputy Chief Minister DK Shiva Kumar the CM in his place.
Both the leaders had a
six-hour meeting with Congress President Mallikarjun Kharge and MP Rahul Gandhi in Delhi on Tuesday.
According to sources,
in the meeting Rahul Gandhi
asked Siddaramaiah to resign from the post of CM and
offered to send him to Rajya Sabha.  Along with this,
he was asked to play a big national role in Delhi.
According to media reports, after discussions with some supporters,
Siddaramaiah said that he would accept the decision of the high command.
He called the
ministers for a breakfast meeting on Thursday morning
and Siddaramaiah may resign on the same day.
Pre-monsoon rains will cover a possible 90% of India from May 29 to June 5.
Monsoon stalled in Kerala due to low humidity.  Temperature reaches
47.4° Celsius in Banda, UP.  Pre-monsoon rains may occur from
May 29 to June 5 in 80 to 90% of the country which is facing severe heat.
This
rain is important because the
monsoon has not yet reached Kerala.  Here, the arrival of monsoon is declared when there is
2.5 mm rainfall for two consecutive days in 14 sub-stations.  The
Meteorological Department had
predicted the arrival of monsoon on May 26.  But due
to weak moisture here, the monsoon could not
move forward.  At the same time, clouds have also weakened due to cyclonic circulation in the south central Arabian Sea.
Europe's weather agency, the European Centre
for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts, has
prepared a 15-day rainfall forecast for India by combining satellite, ocean and atmospheric data.  It indicates heavy rainfall in
South India, East India, Northeast
and Bay of Bengal areas in the next 8 days.
11 people who came to Ahmedabad from African countries are
in isolation.  The government said there are
no cases of Ebola in India.  The report of the woman who returned from Uganda is
negative.
Due to the spread of Ebola virus in African countries,
11 patients who came to Ahmedabad from Uganda, South Sudan and Congo have been
kept in home isolation.
Ahmedabad Corporation official Dr
Bhavin Solanki said that
none of them were found suspicious in the preliminary investigation
but this step has been taken as a precaution.   At the
same time, the Indian government has said that there is
not a single case related to Ebola virus in the country.  The
government had to give this clarification
because
Ebola-like symptoms were seen in a woman who came to India from Uganda.
However, when the test was conducted later, the report
came negative.
Vijayan supporters attacked the ED team,
pelted them with sticks and stones, and damaged their vehicles.  Former Kerala
CM's daughter accused of money laundering,
house raided.  Supporters of former Kerala Chief Minister
Pinarayi Vijayan have
attacked the Enforcement Directorate (ED) team.   A
12-member ED team had reached 10 locations, including
Vijayan's house at Bakery Junction in Thiruvananthapuram, at 7:00 am on Wednesday to conduct
raids in a money laundering case.  This is Vijayan
's rented house.  Vijayan
and his family were present in the house during the raid.  As soon as
this news spread, Vijayan's supporters started gathering outside his house.
When the team came out at around 2:00 pm, it was surrounded by CPI workers.  The
mob
threw stones and bottles at the officers' vehicles.  The
windows of the cars were broken and people were also attacked with sticks.
Today's thought: Problems are
not as powerful as we think they are.  Have you
ever heard that darkness did
not let the morning come?  Do let us know how you liked this video
in the comment section.  If you liked the video then please
like and share the video and to
watch such interesting videos
subscribe to our channel Jio News
and press the bell icon and do check our playlist and community tab to watch our old and
latest videos.
So see you in the next video.
Thank you for now.